(DOCTOR WHO THEME)
Doctor Who (1963)
神秘博士(老版)
The Dominators
(Whopix fan edit)
统领者
(Whopix 粉丝剪辑版)
(Based on English subtitles from opensubtitles.org)
(时间轴/中文翻译: 巴蛮子sz)
Is the local radiation completely absorbed?
本地的辐射已经完全被吸收了吗？
Yes, its energy's been transferred to our fuel reserves.
是的, 它的能量已经转移到我们的燃料储备里了
- But we need much more.
- Of course. That is why we are here.
- 但我们还需要更多 - 当然, 那正是我们来这里的原因
With respect, Navigator Rago,
恕我直言, 导航员 Rago
I still consider we should have continued to Epsilon 4.
我仍然认为我们应该继续探索Epsilon 4号星
I decided otherwise, Probationer Toba.
我做了另外的决定, 实习生 Toba
But this planet has never been fully surveyed.
但这个星球从来没有完整勘察过
It's suitable for our purpose.
The planetary crust is thin here
它很适合我们的目的．这里的地壳很薄
and there's an intelligent form of life
suitable for a workforce.
还有智慧生命可以充当工人
But the natives may not be suitable for slave labour.
Suppose they're hostile?
但本星球人可能用作劳工。假如他们怀有敌意呢？
- If necessary, we shall destroy them.
- Yes, destroy them.
- 必要的话, 我们可以消灭他们  - 是的, 消灭他们
But only if necessary!
Commence work on the preliminary survey.
但只在非常必要的情况下！开始进行初步勘察吧
Command accepted.
接受命令
(WHOOSHING)
(LAUGHING)
Oh, yes. Oh, yes.
噢, 对了, 噢, 对了
(YAWNING)
- Are you still feeling tired, Doctor?
- Yes, just a little bit weary, Jamie.
- 你还是觉得疲惫吗, 博士  - 是的, 有那么一点, Jamie
It's a very exhausting business
真是个很累人的事情
projecting all those mental images, you know.
要投射那么多意识印象
- You need a good rest, Doctor.
- Yes, we all do. A nice holiday.
- 你需要好好休息一下, 博士  - 是, 我们都需要一个美好的假日
Where did you say this place was again?
你刚才说这个地方是哪儿？
Well, the scanner screen in the Tardis
showed it as an island of some sort
哦, TARDIS 里面的扫描屏幕显示出这像是一个岛
surrounded by a sea of mist.
周边是一片薄雾的海洋
Yes, it's an island on Dulkis,
a perfectly splendid planet.
是, 这是 Dulkis 上面的一个岛．Dulkis 是个非常漂亮的星球
I've heard that one before.
我以前听说过
And there won't be any Cybermen or Daleks, will there?
这里不会有赛博人、Dalek 什么的吧, 会吗？
(LAUGHS) No, no, no, of course not.
There's nothing unpleasant on Dulkis.
不, 不, 不, 当然没有．Dulkis上面没有什么让人不愉快的东西
Quarks, destroy the alien vessel.
Quarks, 摧毁那艘外星飞船
(QUARKS BEEPING)
(BUZZING)
Did you say these people were peaceful, Doctor?
你刚才说这里的人都很平和, 博士？
(STUTTERING) Oh, yes, Zoe,
the Dulcians are gentle and friendly.
哦, 是的, Zoe．Dulkis 人都是谦和友好的
Aye, it sounded like it!
是, 听起来像是！
- Did the explosion cause this?
- Oh, no, no, no.
- 是爆炸导致的吗？  - 噢, 不, 不, 不
This was caused by an explosion some time ago, Jamie.
这是好久以前的爆炸导致的, Jamie
Looks like atomic blast damage to me.
我看着像是原子弹爆炸造成的
Yes, I think you're right, Zoe.
是的, 我觉得你说得对, Zoe
But I don't understand it.
但我搞不懂了
Let's look inside, shall we?
我们进去看看, 好吗？
Mind the stuff here.
小心这里的东西
And you destroyed this travel ship?
你摧毁那艘旅行船没有？
You gave me no order to the contrary.
你没有给过我相反的命令啊
You are a probational navigator.
你是一个见习导航员
Your first task is to investigate. Second, assess.
你的第一任务是勘察, 第二, 评估
You allowed your instinct for destruction
你容许了让你那破坏的本能
- to interfere with your primary tasks.
- Not accepted. I did...
- 干扰了你的首要任务  - 不接受．我的确...
How can you assess that which does not exist?
你怎么能够对并不存在的东西进行评估呢？
Have you completed your atomic analysis?
你已经完成原子分析了吗？
Analysis complete.
分析已经完成
Atomic energy released on this island 17.2 decades ago.
这个岛上的原子能量是在 172 年前释放的
A long time. Strange that this should be
the only trace of radiation on this planet.
好久了．奇怪的是这是这个星球上唯一的辐射痕迹
Continue.
继续
Drilling sites have now been located and marked.
钻探地点都已经找到并标记出来了
Then we will examine them.
那我们去检查一下
Did you check the radiation level
before we left the Tardis?
在我们离开 TARDIS 之前我们检查过辐射水平了吗？
That's just what I was thinking, Zoe.
I think I did.
我也正在想这个问题, Zoe．我觉得我检查过了
- Yes, I'm sure I did.
- Hey, what are you two on about?
- 是的, 我确定我检查过了  - 嘿, 你们俩在讨论什么呢？
Well, I was just thinking.
哦, 我只是在想
This place reminds me
of the old atom test islands on Earth.
这个地方让我想起了地球上用于原子弹试验的那些岛屿
Yes. Yes, I think you're right, Zoe.
是的, 是的, 我想你是对的, Zoe
- Test islands?  - For atomic weapons, Jamie.
- 试验岛？  - 用于原子武器的, Jamie
But why on Dulkis?
但为什么 Dulkis 上会有？
They've outlawed war.
No, there must be some other explanation.
他们已经宣布战争为非法了．不, 肯定有其它的解释
Well, I vote we go back to the Tardis
and find somewhere else.
好啦, 我提议我们回到 TARDIS 去, 另外找个地方
Doctor!
博士！
TOBA: This is the eastern drilling site.
这是东端钻取点
- What is that?
- Just a crude, box-like structure.
- 那是什么  - 只是一个天然形成的盒子模样的东西
Shall I summon the Quarks to destroy it?
需要我把 Quarks 唤过来摧毁它吗？
Why? Will it interfere with the work?
为什么？它会干扰我们工作吗？
No, but...
不会, 但是...
Then it would be wasteful to destroy it.
那去摧毁它就是种浪费
(ALL EXCLAIMING)
- Oh, my beautiful coat is all wet.
- Ridiculous.
- 噢, 我漂亮的外套全湿了  - 荒谬
All this is totally unnecessary, you know.
所有这些都是完全没必要的, 知道吗
There's not a trace of contamination on us.
我们身上没有任何污染的痕迹
Yes, so I've noticed. It's odd, isn't it?
是的, 我也注意到了．很奇怪, 对吧？
- What's odd about it?
- Well, the whole island is radioactive.
- 有什么奇怪的？  - 哦, 整个岛都充满了辐射
It has been for 172 years. You must know that.
都已经 172 年了, 你肯定也知道
- Well, it isn't now.  - Of course it is.
- 但, 现在它没有  - 当然有
- Have you checked?  - TEEL: Well, not yet.
- 你检查过了吗？  - 是哦, 还没有
We've only just arrived.
我们才刚刚到这里
But we're taking the annual readings
during the next few days.
但我们要在接下来的几天采集年度数值
Well, if I were you, I'd take them now.
哦, 如果我是你, 我现在就采
Oh, my beautiful trousers.
噢, 我漂亮的裤子
I wasn't aware that anyone else
我倒不知道还会有其他人
had permission to work on the island except ourselves.
有权限在这个岛上工作
Tell me exactly what has been happening.
告诉我到底发生了什么？
But I was hoping you were going to tell us that.
但我还指望你能告诉我们呢
This is an atom test island, isn't it?
这个岛是用于原子弹试验的, 对不？
Oh, but of course. Everybody knows that.
哦, 当然了, 每个人都知道这个
Oh, well, we don't.
哦, 但是, 我们不知道
But atomic weapons on Dulkis?
但是 Dulkis 上面有原子武器？
- I thought war had been abolished here.
- It has.
- 我以为这里已经禁止战争了  - 是禁了
You seem to know surprisingly little
about your own planet.
对于你们自己的星球, 你们似乎知道得出奇的少
Well, that's it, you see.
We've just come in the Tar...
啊, 事实是, 你看, 我们刚刚到达...
Well, as Jamie was about to say,
嗯, 正如 Jamie 刚要说的
we come from a different world, from a different time.
我们来自另外一个世界, 另外一个时间
Not from this world? Really, that's very interesting.
不是来自这个世界？真的吗, 那可真有意思
I must note that in my daily report.
我必须把这个记在我的日报里
Well, you don't sound very surprised.
诶, 你似乎并不感到奇怪
Well, it does explain how you came to
expose yourself to the dangers on this island.
嗯, 这倒的确解释了你们为何让自己暴露于这个岛的危险之中
No Dulcian would do such a foolish thing.
没有那个 Dulkis 人会干这种蠢事
Well, what are you doing here, then?
哦, 那你在这里做什么呢？
We're part of Educator Balan's
expedition from the university.
我们是探险队的, 由大学教育家 Balan带队
But when I was here some time ago,
you were a peaceful race.
但我以前到这里的时候, 你们还是一个和平的种族
- So you've been here before?
- Well, yes.
- 你以前来过这里？  - 嗯, 是的
Ah, I must put that in my...
I'm so sorry. You were saying?
啊, 我必须把这个记进...对不起, 你刚才说什么？
Well, what's happened to you? I thought
aggressive weapons had been abolished.
嗯, 你们发生了什么事？我还以为攻击性武器已经被废止了
Oh, indeed they have.
The second council under Director Olvin.
哦, 他们的确禁了, Olvin 理事的第二议会
He banned the manufacture of all weapons.
他禁掉了所有武器的生产制造
Then what are you doing letting off
atomic devices all over the place?
那你们把原子设备弄得到处都是, 是在做什么呢？
Oh! Oh, there was only one explosion.
哦！ 哦, 只出现了一次爆炸．
Perhaps my pupil, Kando, should explain.
也许我的学生 Kando 可以做出解释
Let's see how much you remember, my dear.
让我们看看你记得多少, 我亲爱的
- Um... Oh, yes.  - The seventh council...
- 唔...噢, 是的  - 第七议会...
The seventh council under Director Manus
由 Manus 领导的第七议会
initiated research which lead to
the development of atomic energy.
启动了科学研究, 从而开始了原子能的发展
- The des...
- BALAN: Destructive capabilities.
- 破... - 破坏能力
The destructive capabilities of this
were immediately apparent and...
这个决定的破坏能力随即出现了, 于是...
BALAN: This island...
这座岛...
And this island was used
to test an explosive device,
于是就用这座岛测试了一次爆炸装置
the results of which can be seen today.
爆炸的结果至今可见到
Thereafter, all further research
into this type of energy was prohibited,
于是, 关于这类能量的所有后续研究都被禁止了
and the island kept as both a museum
and warning for future generations.
这座岛保留成了博物馆, 同时也向后代提供警示作用
Oh, well, she certainly does her homework.
哦, 嗯, 她显然是做了功课的
I see. Then this is an atomic test site?
我明白了．那这就是一个原子试验场了？
Oh, yes. You see, students...
That was really very good, Kando.
噢, 是的．你看, 学生们...这真的很不错, Kando
Students are brought here
to test the radiation level
学生们是被带到这里来测量辐射水平的
and observe the effect on the vegetation.
同时观察植物的生长情况
And of course, to see for themselves
the horrors of atomic destruction.
当然了, 也是为了亲眼看看原子能可怕的毁灭能力
- So there should be radioactivity here?
- But there isn't.
- 所以这里应该是有辐射的？  - 但这里没有
No. I wonder why?
没有．我想问为什么？
Explain.
解释一下
Part of this collection of crude weapons.
原始武器收藏品中的其中一件
Continue.
继续
This one operates on the early laser principle.
这一个依赖于早期的激光原理运作
Fire mechanism here.
这里是开火机关
Self-charging power cell. Limited range.
自动充电电池．射程有限
Is this all you notice?
你留意到的只有这些吗？
The other weapons are just as simple.
其它的武器也一样原始
There's nothing here that could threaten us.
这里没有什么东西能威胁到我们
- These things are so old that if...
- Precisely. Old.
- 这些东西是如此古老以至于..  - 正是, 古老
At last, you casually mention a fact
of major significance.
至少，你无意中提到一个非常重要的事实
Has it not occurred to you,
Probationer Toba,
你有没有想过, 实习生 Toba
that other weapons
must have been developed since these?
在这些武器之后肯定有其它武器发展出来了？
Agreed, Navigator Rago.
同意, 导航员 Rago
DOCTOR: But why do you think
we might be responsible? Thank you.
但是为什么你们觉得我们应该负责？谢谢你
Well, it is conceivable that your craft, the...
是啊, 很容易想到是你们的飞船, 那个...
- Tardis.  -...Tardis,
- TARDIS  - 那个 TARDIS
could have attracted the radioactivity
可能吸收了这些辐射
in much the same way as a magnet attracts metal.
就像一块磁铁吸附金属那样
(CHUCKLES) Oh, it would have registered.
- Do spacecraft often land in Dulkis?
- As far as I know, you are the first.
- 经常有飞船降落在 Dulkis 吗？ - 就我所知, 你们是第一个
I must say, then,
you don't seem the least bit surprised.
那, 我必须说, 你们似乎一点也不惊讶
We are taught to accept fact,
我们早被教导为接受事实
it being foolish to contemplate fantasy
in the face of reality.
在现实面前琢磨那些假想的事情是愚蠢的
You are here. This is fact.
你们到了这里, 这就是事实
That you come from another planet I accept,
你们来自于另外一个星球, 这我接受
because I have no other means of proving it.
因为我也没有其它手段来证明
- TEEL: Not a sign of radiation.
- BALAN: There.
- 一点辐射也没有  - 那里
But look what I found.
看看我找到了什么？
- Cully, what are you...
- Never mind that now.
- Cully, 你在做... - 先别管那个
We've got to get back to the capital.
我们得回到首都去
Oh, it's impossible.
We haven't even begun our survey yet.
噢, 这不可能．我们都还没有开始我们的调查
Well, if you don't, you'll be wiped out.
但是, 如果你们不回去, 你们全都会被消灭的
He claims to have seen robots and spacecraft.
他宣称说看到了机器人和飞船
- You didn't tell me you brought robots.
- I haven't.
- 你没有告诉我你还带了机器人来  - 我没带
Look, I brought three people here in my ship.
听着, 我的飞船就带了三个人到这里来
They've been killed by those creatures.
So if you don't...
他们被那些家伙杀死了．所以如果你不...
(LAUGHING)
- ZOE: What's so funny?
- Now, I see. Ajest.
- 什么这么好笑？  - 啊, 我明白了．笑话
Three people. So you come
from another world, do you, Doctor?
三个人．所以你们是从另外一个世界来的, 是吗, 博士？
- Hey, I don't think...
- Really, Cully,
- 嘿, 我不认为...  - 真的, Cully
you and your friends might at least
have agreed upon the same story.
你和你的朋友们至少应该先勾兑一下故事的说法
What? But these aren't my three, you old...
什么？但这并不是我那三个人, 你个老...
Oh, what's the use?
哦, 这是做什么用的？
- JAMIE: What was he talking about?
- I don't know.
- 他在说什么啊？  - 我不知道
Look, I've never seen
this gentleman before in my life.
听着, 我这辈子从来没见过这位先生
Cully, you had no right to bring
these people here without permission,
Cully, 你不能未获得任何授权就带这三个人到这里来
even if you are the son
of the director of the council.
即便你是议长的儿子也不行
Well, go on, then.
Why don't you call him up?
好, 那就去啊．你为什么不给他打电话？
At least he's not as stupid as you are.
至少他不像你这么蠢
- You say you've seen a spacecraft?
- I've told you, haven't I?
- 你说你看见了一艘飞船？  - 我跟你说过吧？
And robots. Well, at least I think
they were robots.
还有机器人．哦, 至少我认为它们是机器人
What exactly did this spacecraft look like?
那艘飞船具体是什么样子的？
Well, it's large and circular
and a sort of silvery colour.
哦, 巨大的圆形, 带着某种银色
That means it can't be the Tardis.
那就是说不可能是我们的 TARDIS
Are you sure it wasn't square,
like a large wooden box?
你确定它不是方的, 看起来像一个木头盒子？
No, no, that's not the spacecraft.
不, 不, 那不是我说的飞船
No, the box is where
those aliens have made a sort of mark,
不, 那些外星人在那个盒子附近做了某种标记
a five-pointed star.
像一颗５个点的星形
They were examining it just now.
Talking about destroying it.
他们正在检查那个盒子, 在讨论是否摧毁它
- What?  - What?
- 什么？  - 什么？
- Jamie, we better go and see.
- Come on.
- Jamie, 我们最好去看看  - 快点
You're wasting your time.
你这是在浪费时间
I prefer to make up my own mind, thank you.
我更喜欢自己做决定, 谢谢你了
Jamie. Are you coming, Zoe?
Jamie. 你来吗, Zoe?
- No, I think I'll stay here.  - Right.
- 不, 我觉得我还是留在这里  - 好
- Come on, then.
- We shan't be a minute.
- 快点, 来  - 我们马上就来
Commence work on preparing the sites
of the outer bore hole.
开始为外面的钻孔做准备工作
- At once, Navigator Rago.
- Send this message to Fleet Leader.
- 马上, 导航员 Rago  - 发送下述消息给舰队头目
"Materials located. Detailed report follows."
"已经定位到材料．详细报告随后提交＂
Command accepted.
接受命令
JAMIE: At least they haven't harmed the Tardis.
至少他们还没有伤害 TARDIS
DOCTOR: That's a relief.
这放心了
Jamie, come and have a look at this.
It's interesting.
Jamie, 过来看看这个, 很有意思
- Look. See. - What?
- 喏, 看到没  - 什么?
What's so interesting about that?
哪有什么奇怪的？
Well, I think it must be
some sort of survey mark.
这个, 我觉得这是在做某种勘察留下的印记
Very likely.
很有可能
Jamie, look.
Jamie, 看
- Some sort of tracks.  - So they are.
- 像是某种脚印  - 还真是
We'll follow them, shall we?
我们跟踪一下, 该跟吗？
Oh, look, I think we'd better get back.
噢, 你看, 我觉得我们最好回去
Zoe will be wondering what's happening...
Zoe可能在嘀咕我们怎么样了...
Well, this is interesting. Yes.
嗯, 这有点意思, 是的
Obviously an interstellar spaceship
of considerably advanced design.
显然这艘星际飞船有着相当先进的设计
Oh, no. You're not thinking
what I think you're thinking, are you?
噢, 别, 你不是在想我觉得你在想的事情吧, 是吗？
That, I think, Jamie, depends
on what you think I am thinking.
那就, 我觉得, 取决于你觉得我在想什么
Oh.
哦
- Hey, Doctor. - Stop that, Jamie.
- 嘿, 博士  - 别那样, Jamie
- Doctor. - Jamie, don't do it.
- 博士  - Jamie, 别那样
- Doctor, look. Look.  - Oh, my word.
- 博士, 看, 看  - 噢, 天啦
QUARK: Do not move. Do not move.
不许动, 不许动
Next task?
下个任务是？
Shall we destroy?
需要我们消灭吗？
Oh, good heavens!
噢, 老天！
Look, what's going on? Who are you?
诶, 这怎么回事？你们是谁？
We are Dominators.
我们是统领者
Both of you stand by that wall.
你们俩都靠那面墙去站着
- I will not.
- Oh, now, Jamie...
- 我不去  - 噢, 现在 Jamie...
- Oh, no. They're not going to...
- We're meant to be obeyed.
- 噢, 不好, 他们不是要...  - 必须服从我们
- Not by me, you're not.
- DOCTOR: Jamie!
- 我可不干, 你别想  - Jamie!
What... All right, if you insist.
什么...好吧, 如果你们非得这样
(WARBLING)
Doctor, I can't move. Help me!
博士, 我动不了了, 帮我！
(DOCTOR EXCLAIMING)
It is pointless to struggle.
挣扎是没有意义的
My Quarks have used a molecular force
to bind your bodies to the wall.
我的夸克用了一种分子力将你们与那赌面墙绑到一起
What's he going to do with us?
他打算对我们干什么？
Alien races are occasionally of use to us.
外星种族偶尔对我们也是有用的
I intend to probe your physiological makeup.
我打算要探究一下你的生理结构
Do what?
做什么？
- Doctor, can you not do anything?
- Don't struggle, Jamie. Keep still.
- 博士, 你不能做点什么吗？  - 别挣扎, Jamie, 静静呆着
Toba. Quarks, attach force units.
Toba. 夸克, 加载强制设备
- Activate. -(WARBLING)
激活
RAGO: Visor.
面罩
Transmatter focus probe.
fixme
Brittle skeletal structure.
易碎的骨骼结构
Reasonable flexibility.
灵活性尚可
Certain amount of muscular force,
could be marginally useful.
肌肉有一些力量, 可能有一点用途
- Vulnerable, only one heart.
- TOBA: Intelligence?
- 脆弱, 只有一个心脏  - 智力呢？
A simple brain. Signs of recent rapid learning.
大脑简单．有近期快速成长的迹象
Still, somewhat crude.
但还是, 比较原始
Shall I prepare the other specimen for scrutiny?
我应该准备好另外那个标本进行检查吗？
No, they will be identical.
不用了, 他们会是一样的
Conserve power.
节省点能量吧
- TOBA: Are they dangerous?
- No, they are physically inferior.
- 他们危险吗？  - 不危险, 他们体能比较差
- So we destroy them?  - No.
- 那我们消灭他们？  - 不要
- It is possible we may use them.
- What for?
- 我们还是有可能利用他们的  - 用来做什么？
- Workforce.  - We've got the Quarks.
- 用作劳力  - 但我们有夸克啊
We must conserve their power, you know that.
我们必须节约它们的能量, 你知道的
But why do you want...
但为什么你想要...
Command accepted.
接受命令
Set up a reaction test.
准备一个反应测试
Test this one.
测测这个
As soon as your friends return,
等你的朋友们一返回
they will follow you and Cully
in the second capsule.
他们就会坐第二辆穿梭车来找你和Cully
Wouldn't it be better
if all four of us went together?
如果我们四个人一起走不是更好？
- Travel capsules only take two.
- Number one ready.
- 旅行穿梭车只能坐两个人  - 一号已经就绪
There's nothing to be afraid of, you know.
没什么可害怕的, 知道吗
Oh, I'm not frightened.
I'm looking forward to it.
噢, 我不害怕．反而很期待
Come on, let's try and stir up
a bit of action in the capital.
来吧, 我们试试看能否在首府搞出点事情
You really mustn't believe
Cully's wild tales.
你真的不能相信 Cully 那些天马行空的故事
(DOOR HUMMING)
I will dial for the capital, Cully,
if you don't mind.
我要拨通首府, Cully, 如果你不介意的话
I see. Frightened I might disappear, eh?
我明白了, 害怕我可能会消失, 嗯？
Well, it has been known, hasn't it, Cully?
哦, 大家都知道的, 是吗, Cully?
It'd be a joke if it happened
this time, though, wouldn't it?
如果这次发生的话就会是个笑话, 是吧？
And if we are to use these Dulcians as slaves,
而且如果我们要用 Dulkis 人作为奴隶
there are certain qualities you must look for.
有一些品质你肯定得寻找
Obedience, strength, sufficient intelligence
to make them of use,
服从, 有力气, 有足够的智力以便我们能利用
but not so much as to make them dangerous.
Is that clear?
但也不能太高以免带来危险．明白了吗？
Yes.
好的
Uh, what are they saying?
啊, 他们在说些什么？
I think they are arranging
for some sort of test.
我觉得他们在组织某种测试
- Test? What for?  - I don't know.
- 测试？为了什么？  - 我不知道
I thought I heard them
mention the word "intelligence".
我觉得我听到他们提到了＂智力＂这个词
Oh, you mean they're going to
find out how clever we are?
噢, 你的意思是他们想搞明白我们有多聪明？
Yes. Or how stupid.
是的．或者是有多蠢
I wonder which is the more important to them?
我在想哪个对他们更重要？
Well, then, Zoe, what were you doing on the island?
好, 那么, Zoe, 你们在那个岛上做什么？
Well, nothing, really, just looking around.
哦, 没什么, 真的, 就四周看看
- But didn't you know it was dangerous?
- No. At least not at first.
- 但你们不知道它很危险？  - 不知道, 至少一开始不知道
Oh, Cully, how can your conscience allow you
噢, Cully, 你的良心怎么能够允许
to expose innocent and foolish people
to such dangers?
把天真愚蠢的人带入如此危险的地方呢？
- But I didn't take her to the island.
- Oh, nonsense.
- 但我没有带她去岛上  - 噢, 胡说
I know all about Cully's Adventures Unlimited.
我可知道 ＂Cully探险无极限＂是什么
- You know, but why didn't you...
- Well, you weren't doing any harm.
- 你是知道, 但你为什么不...  - 还好, 你没有造成什么伤害
- At least we thought you weren't.
- But it's illegal.
- 至少我们觉得没有  - 但这不合法
To prosecute would have given you open publicity
起诉你正好顺了你意, 给了你面对公众的机会
and it wouldn't have reflected very well on me, either.
而且对我的影响也不好
I see. Why can't I be treated as an individual
我明白了．为什么我就不能被当作一个普通人
and not always as the son of the Director?
而不要总是被当作议长的儿子看待呢？
Now then, young lady, tell me exactly what happened.
现在, 女士, 确切地告诉我都发生了什么？
Well, I landed with the Doctor and Jamie.
哦, 我和博士、Jamie 一起降落到这里
- In Cully's ship, yes?  - Cully?
- 坐着 Cully 的飞船, 是吗?  - Cully?
- Oh, no. We came in the Tardis.
- And what is that?
- 哦, 不, 我们坐 TARDIS 来的  - 那是什么？
- It's an advanced craft for travel.
- Goes through time and space.
- 是一种先进的旅行船  - 可在时间和空间里穿梭
I think this joke has gone far enough.
我觉得这个玩笑开得过火了
There you are, I knew he wouldn't believe it.
看吧, 我就知道他不会相信的
But it's true! You can ask the Doctor and Jamie,
但这是真的！你可以去问博士和 Jamie
they'll be here soon.
他们很快就会到这里了
What do you hope to gain by this foolishness?
你编这些鬼话是图什么呢？
But it's not. I told you when
we spoke on the vision link.
不是鬼话, 我们在视频电话里对话时我就告诉你了
Three people have been killed,
a spacecraft has landed,
有三个人丧命了, 一艘飞船降落了
radioactivity has disappeared
and there are robots on that island.
辐射消失了, 岛上出现了一些机器人
Now, I may have a pretty inventive mind,
喏, 我可能是有一个异想天开的脑袋
but I wouldn't have dreamt up
that lot, now, would I?
但我不会做梦做到这个程度, 对吧？
And no doubt you will confirm all this?
毫无疑问, 你可以证实所有这些吧？
Uh, well, I haven't actually seen
the spacecraft and robots...
啊, 只是, 我其实还没有看见飞船和机器人
Oh, so it seems we only have
your word for it, Cully.
噢, 那我们就只有你的证言了, Cully
And experience has taught us
how little that can be relied upon.
而经验已经教给我们, 那些话有多么可值得信赖
What's he up to now?
他现在要做什么？
He's arranging some sort of
intelligence test, Jamie.
他要搞某种智力测试, Jamie
JAMIE: You mean those wee shapes
in that big box? What for?
你是说那个大盒子里面那些小积木？什么目的？
Yes, well, we'll have to put
the right shapes into the correct holes,
是的, 嗯, 我们必须把积木放入形状对应的小洞里面去
it's quite simple.
相当简单的
Well, if that's all it is,
a kid of two could do it.
哦, 如果仅此而已, 一个两岁的小孩都可以搞定
Yes, that's what bothering me.
It's too simple.
是的, 这是困扰我的地方．它太简单了
You moved.
你动了
I'm free. What about you?
我松开了．你怎么样？
- Me, too.  - Come on.
- 我也是  - 快点
(QUARK BEEPING)
TOBA: Well?
QUARK: Molecular force expended.
- 怎样？  - 分子力已经消耗完了
Order required.
请给出指令
-Are the specimens to be refused?
-No.
- 需要拒绝这些标本吗？  - 不用
- What are you going to do with us?
- Quiet! Over there.
- 你打算拿我们怎样？  - 安静！到那边去
Sit.
坐下
Well, thank you.
好, 谢谢你
Attach force units.
加载强制设施
(HUMMING)
Hands. Through there.
两手, 穿过那里
Power.
通电
(BUZZING, DOCTOR EXCLAIMING)
That will be repeated at regular intervals
那会隔一段时间重复一下
until the puzzle is reassembled.
直到该谜题被解开
(WHIMPERING) Oh, no!
噢, 不要！
Begin.
开始
(GRUNTS)
JAMIE: Hurry up, Doctor.
快点, 博士
(BUZZING, DOCTOR EXCLAIMING)
DOCTOR: Oh, my hands!
JAMIE: No, the square bit...
- 噢, 我的手！  - 不, 方的那个...
- DOCTOR: What?
- JAMIE: No, not the star,
- 什么？  - 不, 不是星形那个
the square bit in there!
那边那个方形的
(BUZZING, DOCTOR EXCLAIMING)
Detach.
松开
Doctor. Doctor.
博士, 博士
Now, where's that...
诶, 哪儿去了那个...
Here. Take it. Sniff, sniff.
这里, 来, 嗅一下, 嗅一下
-(DOCTOR COUGHING)
-That's it.
好了
Come away. Come away
from that fearful contraption.
闪开, 别靠近那个可怕的东西
- You all right?  - Yes, I'm all right.
- 你没事吧？  - 是的, 我没事
What were you up to? That puzzle was easy.
你在搞些什么啊？那个谜题很简单啊
An unintelligent enemy is far less dangerous
一个不聪明的敌人其危险性要小得多...
than an intelligent one, Jamie.
比起聪明的家伙来, Jamie
- Hey?  - Just act stupid.
- 嘿？  - 只管装傻
- Do you think you can manage that?
- Oh, aye, it's easy...
- 你觉得你能搞定那个吗？  - 哦, 是的, 很简单...
Attach force units.
加载强制装置
You two, over here. Sit!
你们俩, 过来．坐下！
- Oh, thank you.  - Thank you. Oh.
- 噢, 谢谢你  - 谢谢你, 啊
Power.
通电
Now, get off.
现在, 下来
(ELECTRICITY CRACKLING, DOCTOR YELLING)
- I said, get off. - Oh, but...
- 我说了, 下来  - 哦, 但是...
(ELECTRICITY CRACKLING, BOTH EXCLAIMING)
- Try it round here.  - You're surrounded.
- 试试走这边  - 你被围住了
- Well, how do we get off?
- There is a way, find it!
- 那, 我们怎么下来？  - 有一种方法, 找出来！
- Test complete?
- TOBA: These creatures are useless.
- 测试结束了吗？  - 这些生物没什么用
- Strange.  - You question my report, Navigator Rago?
- 奇怪  - 你质疑我的报告吗, 导航员 Rago?
I find it at variance with what we already know.
我发现这跟我们已经知道的情况不符
- I don't understand.
- The weapons we saw earlier,
- 我不明白  - 我们早先看见的武器
could they have been devised by such apparent simpletons?
它们可能会是这么明显的傻瓜设计出来的吗？
- You think that there were...
- That we will find out.
- 你觉得他们是在...  - 我们得去探究明白
Message to fleet leader.
传送信息给舰队首领
"Materials readily accessible, please proceed to refuel.
＂原料已可获取, 请前来补给能量＂
"Investigating potential slave labour." Transmit.
＂正在调查奴役劳工的可行性＂, 发送
(DEVICE BEEPS) Come with me.
跟我来
- But every time we try and get up...
- Jump!
- 但每次我们试图起来... 跳！
DOCTOR: Jump?
跳？
Jump.
跳
(BOTH EXCLAIM)
A simple circuit completed by your bodies,
你们的身体接通了这个简单的电路
you obviously know little of electricity.
显然你们对电力基本不懂
Elec... Elec...
电...电...
Are you such a fool?
You have intelligent eyes.
你真是这么蠢吗？你有一双聪明的眼睛
I will continue the test personally.
我得自己来继续这项测试
- RAGO: I said, what is that?
- Well, it's some sort of gun, isn't it?
- 我说过了, 那是什么？  - 哦, 是一种枪, 对吧？
- Explain it to me.
- Well, I don't know that I...
- 给我解释一下  - 哦, 我不知道我...
- Firepower potential?  - Huh?
- 火力?  - 哈
- What does it do?  - Oh! Oh, I see.
- 它是做什么的？  - 噢！哦, 我知道了
Well, guns kill people.
对, 枪可以杀人
- Is that what you wanted to know?  - Fire it.
- 你们是不是想知道这个？  - 开枪
Well, I don't think...
这, 我不觉得...
You have to put something into it first
and it comes out here,
你必须先放点东西进去, 然后它从这里出来
as far as I remember.
我记得是这样
You. Fire it.
你，开枪
- Oh, I wouldn't know how...
- Do as Dominator Rago says. Fire it!
- 哦, 我不知道怎么... - 按统领者 Rago 说的做, 开枪！
(STAMMERING) Well, I'll try. Um...
好, 我试试．唔..
I think you put a cork
or something in...in there...
我记得你要放一个木塞什么的到...这里...
Jamie. Jamie, be careful.
Jamie, Jamie, 小心一点
- I'll get the hang of it, Doctor.
- Jamie, be careful.
- 我会想起来的, 博士  - Jamie, 小心一点
Wait, we don't understand guns on Dulkis.
等等, 我们 Dulkis 星上面的人都不懂用枪
We haven't used them for hundreds of years.
我们已经几百年都没有使用过了
So,
这么说
you don't understand guns.
你们不懂用枪
(EXCLAIMING)
Are you sure?
你肯定吗？
Yes! It was the clever ones who invented them.
是的！是那些聪明人发明了他们
- The clever ones?  - Yes, they...
- 聪明人？  - 是的, 他们...
They lived long ago, you see.
There aren't many of them left.
那是很久以前的事了, 你看．他们现在没几个人了
They stopped us using guns and things.
他们不让我们用枪这些东西了
- There are two distinct types on this planet?
- Yes!
- 这个星球上有两类不同的人？  - 正是！
How many of these clever ones are there?
这些聪明人还有多少？
Well, there are not many.
We don't like them much.
哦, 并不太多．我们不太喜欢他们
- They tell us what to do, you see.  - Good.
- 他们告诉我们该怎么做, 你看  - 很好
I see.
我明白了
There is nothing to fear from these primitives,
对于这些原始人没有什么可害怕的
and the others sound as if they're pacifists.
另外那些听起来像是和平主义者
So they are useless.
所以 他们都没有什么用
They have a small labour potential, nothing more.
他们只有微弱的劳工潜质, 很有限
- Shall I destroy them?
- No, we must conserve power.
- 那我该消灭他们吗？  - 不, 我们必须节约能量
- But why do...
- We have nothing to fear from such creatures
- 但为社会那么...  - 我们不用怕这些生物
It will be a waste of energy to destroy them.
消灭他们也将是对能量的浪费
Leave them!
别管他们了
Stay away from us and the Quarks.
离我们远点, 离夸克也远点
- Oh, yes, sir. Thank you very much.
- Yes, Master.
- 噢, 好的先生, 非常感谢  - 遵命, 主人
(DOCTOR SIGHING)
- Am I glad that's over.
- Yeah, me, too.
- 很高兴终于结束了  - 是啊, 我也是
They're a bloodthirsty lot,
these Dominators, aren't they?
他们是帮嗜血的家伙, 这些统领者, 是不？
Aye. What do you think they're after?
是．你觉得他们有什么企图？
I don't know.
我不知道
That message they sent.
他们发的那条消息
"Material readily accessible."
"原料已可获取"
Some sort of mineral deposits, do you think?
像是在挖什么矿, 你说呢？
Then this fleet of theirs would refuel,
land and pick it up. It makes sense.
然后他们的舰队就会来补给能量, 登陆把它取走．有点道理
What do they want the Dulcians
as slaves for? They've got the Quarks.
他们为什么想让这些 Dulkis 人做奴隶？他们已经有夸克了
Aye, nasty little beasties.
是, 很恶心的小怪兽
Hey, Doctor, they've gone.
嘿, 博士, 他们已经走了
We'd better get back to that survey place,
Zoe will be wondering what's happened to us.
我们最好回到勘察点去, Zoe该担心我们怎么样了
I think you're right.
我觉得你说得对
I've got to make them believe me,
before it's too late.
我得让他们相信我, 否则就来不及了
- Well, what are you going to do?
- Get some evidence.
- 那, 你打算做什么？  - 找点证据
Will you come back to the island with me?
你愿意跟我一起回到岛上去吗？
All right. But how do we get past
the council out there?
好啊, 但我们怎么绕过外面的议会呢？
Through my father's rooms. Come on.
穿过我父亲的房间, 快点
We'll have to steal a travel capsule somehow.
我们必须得想法偷一辆旅行穿梭车
Well, I can manage that all right, but...
哦, 我可以搞定那个, 但是...
- Well, what's the matter?  - Your clothes.
- 怎么, 什么问题？  - 你的衣服
- Not exactly Dulcian, are they?  - So?
- 很不像 Dulkis 人风格, 是不？  - 那怎样？
We'll attract too much attention.
我们太引人注目了
We'll never get past the capsule managers.
我们永远没法通过穿梭车管理员那一关
Still, no problem.
好了, 没问题
We can always fix you up
with some Dulcian garments.
我们还是可以修正这个问题, 弄点 Dulkis 人的衣服
- Where from? - Clothing dispenser unit.
- 哪儿有？  - 服装分发部
There's one in my father's rooms. Come on.
我父亲房间里面就有一个, 快来
This will take you direct to the capital, Doctor.
这可以直接带你去首府, 博士
Your young friend Zoe is already there.
你年轻的朋友 Zoe 已经在那里了
And no doubt Director Senex
is awaiting your arrival now.
而且议长 Senex 无疑也在等着你的到来
- Oh, this is splendid. (CHUCKLES)
- Hey, Doctor, what is this?
- 哦, 这太帮了  - 嘿, 博士, 这是什么？
You know I hate being put in a remote...
你知道我讨厌坐进一个远程...
Now, perhaps we can get on with our work.
现在, 也许我们可以继续工作了
QUARK: Unknown creatures approaching.
有不明生物靠近
-TOBA: Destroy?  - No.
- 消灭？  - 不
Investigate.
先调查
- It's enormous.  - So Cully was telling the truth.
- 很巨大  - 看来 Cully 说的是实话
- BALAN: Was he?  - TEEL: But Balan...
- 是吗？  - 但是 Balan
Where are the robots?
机器人都在哪儿？
Inside, perhaps?
里面, 也许吧？
But it's empty.
但里面是空的
Look, there's a map of the island.
看, 这里有这个岛的地图
QUARK: Stand still.
站着别动
But you are not Dulcians!
但你们不是 Dulkis 星人!
Where do you think everybody is?
你觉得所有人都哪儿去了？
Destroy.
消灭！
Destroy!
(QUARKS WARBLING)
- Cully, what's happening?  - I don't know.
- Cully, 发生了什么？  - 我不知道
- ZOE: Oh!  - CULLY: The door. Quick!
- 噢！  - 去门那儿, 快！
Stuck. It's stuck.
卡住了, 门卡住了
We're trapped.
我们被困死了
Recharge.
重新装载
(QUARKS HUMMING)
Complete destruction.
彻底毁灭
Maybe you'll believe in my robots now.
也许你现在相信我说的机器人了
I don't know about robots,
but something was attacking us,
我不知道机器人什么的, 但的确有谁在攻击我们
and with pretty sophisticated weapons, too.
而且有着相当尖端的武器
Well, whatever it was,
we'd better get out of here fast.
哦, 不管它是什么, 我们最好尽快离开这里
Let's try and move this door.
我们试试能否挪动这道门
Unnecessary destruction is wasteful.
Did you inspect it?
不必要地毁灭是种浪费．你检查过吗？
All relevant details have been recorded.
所有相关细节都已经记录下来了
See if there are any survivors
and bring them to me.
看看是否还有幸存者, 带他们来见我
Alive.
要活的
- Come on! Keep it... - Oh!
- 加油！撑住...  - 噢！
From your reaction
根据你们的反应
and your lack of knowledge
of the way of life on Dulkis,
以及你们对 Dulkis 星球的生活方式知之甚少
it would seem there is some truth in your story
看起来你的故事里面有些可信的地方
that you're from another planet.
你似乎的确来自另外一个星球
Of course there's some truth!
当然是可信的！
Look, it was your people who thought
we were friends of Cully's.
看, 是你们的人认为我们是 Cully 的朋友
The identity of my son's companions
can now be established,
我儿子这些同伴的身份现在可以确认了
though what has happened to them
is not quite clear.
不过他们身上发生了什么还不是特别清楚
But Cully has told you they were murdered.
但 Cully 告诉过你他们都被杀了
And I believe him!
并且我相信他！
(COUNCILLORS MURMURING) Why?
为什么？
Because I have seen these Dominators!
因为我见过这些统领者！
We were just taken aboard their spacecraft.
我们还被带上了他们的飞船
Believe me, they're callous, without pity!
相信我, 他们非常冷血, 毫无怜悯！
(COUNCILLORS MURMURING)
I would be grateful if you could tell me
what occurred on the island.
如果你能告诉我们那个岛上发生了什么, 我会很感激的
Oh, look here, we've told you!
哦, 看这儿, 我们告诉过你！
We're just wasting time talking
while Zoe's in danger!
我们在这里闲谈浪费时间, 而 Zoe 正处于危险之中！
Can't we get away?
我们不能逃走啊？
Oh, we wouldn't stand a chance.
These Quarks are deadly.
噢, 我们一点机会也没有．那些夸克很要命
- Any idea how they're powered?  - No. Why?
- 知道它们是用什么能量的吗？  - 不知道, 怎么？
Well, if we knew, we might be able
to put them out of action.
哦, 如果我们知道, 也许我们就可以让它们停止工作
Attack them? Are you out of your mind?
袭击它们？你疯了吗？
Well, they're only robots.
哼, 他们只是机器人而已
"Only"?
而已？
Do you really think we could destroy one?
你真的认为我们可以消灭一个？
It'd be easier if we had a gun of some...
如果我们有枪的话, 应该会容易一点...
- The laser gun!  - Eh?
- 激光枪！  - 嗯？
Cully, I think we stand a chance.
Cully, 我想我们有点机会了
TOBA: Take them to the others.
带他们去其他人那里
QUARK: Move.
走
I'll set them to work on the drilling site.
我会让他们在钻取点工作
Work potential and stamina
to be recorded and sent for analysis.
将工作潜力和耐力记录下来, 送去分析
Agreed. If any of them should escape...
同意．如果有任何人逃跑...
Then you will report the fact to me,
no personal action.
那你就将情况报告给我, 不要擅自行动
(SHOUTS) Toba!
Toba!﻿
Command accepted.
命令已接受
Hey, would you look down there?
嘿, 你看一下那下面?
That's the ruined building. Hello.
那是被毁的建筑．你好
What can you see?
你看到了什么？
- JAMIE: It's Zoe and Cully!
- We've got to get down there!
- 是 Zoe 和 Cully!  - 我们得去那下面！
Jamie, we'll split up
and get round the back of them.
Jamie, 我们得分开, 绕到他们后面去
- I'll cut across those cliffs.
- I'll go this way.
- 我从那些峭壁抄过去  - 我走这边
- Ready?  - Yes.
- 准备好了吗？  - 是的
Once you're inside, give me time to
get the two Quarks into your line of fire.
等你进去以后, 给我点时间让我把两个夸克弄到你的火力点上去
Here we go.
我们来了
(GRUNTS)
(EXCLAIMS)
This one collapsed.
这个崩溃了
Join the other specimens.
去跟其他标本呆一起吧
This is foolishness, Cully.
这很愚蠢, Cully
All clear.
安全
Best of luck.
运气非常好
What do you think you're doing?
Zoe's out there!
你知道自己在干什么吗？Zoe 在那边！
I know that, you fool,
I was aiming at those Quarks.
我知道, 你个蠢人．我瞄准的是那些夸克
QUARK: All specimens stand up!
所有标本都站起来！
TOBA: What are you doing?
你要做什么？
You were told to keep away from the Quarks.
都告诉过你要离那些夸克远点
Oh, but I do.
噢, 我是的啊
Whenever I see one, I go away.
我看见一个, 我就走开
But they're all over the island,
where can I go?
但它们在这个岛上到处都是, 我能走哪里去呢？
Stop! One of them is missing.
停下！他们中有一个不见了
The man Cully has escaped.
那个叫 Cully 的逃走了
Has he?
是吗？
It's no good, Jamie.
We daren't wait any longer.
这可不妙, Jamie, 我们不敢再等着了
Something must have happened to the Doctor.
博士那边肯定出状况了
I think you're right.
我觉得你说对了
- TOBA: Cully! - Down!
- Cully!  - 趴下！
I told you to stay away from the window.
我告诉过你要离窗户远点
- Do you think he saw me?
- TOBA: I know you're in there, Cully!
- 你觉得他看到我了吗？  - 我知道你在里面, Cully!
Give me that.
把那个给我
Now you'll see what happens when
the orders of a Dominator are disobeyed!
现在你将会看到, 不遵从统领者的命令将会怎样！
Quark, destroy!
夸克, 毁灭！
(WARBLING)
Right. Here goes.
好了, 开始了
(LASER GUN FIRING)
(WARBLING INCOHERENTLY)
Destroy! Destroy!
消灭！消灭！
(QUARKS WARBLING)
(EXPLOSIONS)
- Let's get out of here.
- CULLY: No! This way.
- 我们离开这里  - 不！这边
Stop.
停下
QUARK: On the orders of Dominator Toba,
按统领者 Toba 的命令
the building was destroyed,
该建筑已被摧毁
also the man Cully.
以及人类 Cully
- But Jamie was in that building!
- Silence!
- 但 Jamie 在那个建筑里！ - 安静！
You deliberately disobeyed my order?
你故意不遵守我的命令？
My life was threatened
and the Quark destroyed.
我的性命受到了威胁，夸克摧毁了它
Yes, because of your own actions.
是的，因为你擅自行动
Are you suggesting
I should have let him escape?
你是在暗示我应该放任他逃走？
And where would he have gone?
We are on an island, Toba.
他又能跑哪儿去？我们在一个岛上，Toba
These creatures cannot escape.
这些生物逃不了
Now listen to me carefully,
现在仔细听我说
and this time you will obey my instructions.
这一次你要服从我的指示
Send these creatures back
to the central bore position.
把这些家伙送回中央矿洞位置
I want it cleared, ready for drilling.
我期望那里清理处理，为钻孔做好准备
But the Quarks will do it more quickly.
但夸克可以做得更快
We must conserve their energy
for drilling purposes.
我们必须保留他们的能量，留给钻孔用
You know the power levels are low.
你知道它们的能量值很低
Hey, Cully, would you look who's here?
嘿, Cully, 你看看谁来了？
Any Quarks?
还有夸克吗？
- CULLY: Yes, one.  - JAMIE: Hmm.
- 是的, 有一个  - 唔
CULLY: No, there's more. Can't quite see,
不, 还有好些, 看不太清楚
but I think they're working at something
just outside the building.
但我觉得它们就在楼外面干什么活
JAMIE: Let's have a look.
我们来看一眼
They don't seem to have harmed anybody.
他们似乎没有伤害谁
Well, Balan isn't there.
好, Balan 不在那里
He's probably working somewhere else.
他很可能在别的什么地方干活
- Look, Cully...  - What now?
- 看, Cully...  - 现在怎样？
We can't just let them stay up there, can we?
我们不能让他们待在那上面, 是吧？
- Well, what can we do?
- Get them down here with us.
- 那, 我们怎么办？  - 把他们弄下来跟我们待一起
- But what about the Quarks?  - Well, we'll...
- 但夸克怎么对付？  - 这样, 我们...
Here we go again.
我们又来了
- Operate! -(WHIRRING)
开动！
- Doctor? - Hmm?
- 博士?  - 唔？
What are they doing?
他们在做什么？
They're drilling.
在钻孔
Well, yes, I know that, but what for?
啊, 是, 我知道这个, 但钻孔做什么？
Hmm?
嗯？
I don't think they want to take
anything out of the Earth, Zoe,
我觉得他们不是想从地里取什么东西出来, Zoe
rather put something into it.
而是要放什么东西进去
- Well, what?  - Well, if I'm right...
- 但, 是怎么呢？  - 哦, 如果我是对的...
Oh, no!
噢, 不！
(MOUTHING)
(QUARK BLEEPING)
Excuse me...
原谅我...
QUARK: Do not move!
不许动!
Oh!
哦!
(QUARK ALARM BUZZING)
- Right, Cully!  - Quick, follow me!
- 好了, Cully!  - 快, 跟着我！
- Don't just stand there, go on!  - Quick!
- 别在那里傻站着, 走啊！  - 快！
Cease drilling!
停止钻取！
A Quark is being attacked! Follow!
一个夸克被袭击了！跟上！
Quarks, search and destroy!
夸克们, 搜索、消灭！
Quark, where are the prisoners?
夸克, 那些囚徒都去哪儿了？
QUARK: Out of action.
有故障
No recorded data.
没有数据记录
They can't be far away. They must be hiding.
他们不可能跑远, 肯定是躲起来了
Quarks, search and destroy!
夸克们, 搜索、消灭！
Command countermanded!
撤回命令！
Why has the drilling stopped again, Toba?
钻孔为什么又停下来了, Toba?
The prisoners have attacked
a Quark and escaped!
那些囚徒袭击了一个夸克, 然后逃跑了！
And once again you've dropped
everything to hunt them!
而你又一次放下了所有事情去追他们！
I have just completed calculating
the remaining power levels of the Quark force.
我刚刚对夸克的剩余能量值完成了计算
Thanks to your foolish actions,
they are dangerously low!
多亏了你的愚蠢行为, 它们的值现在低得危险！
All efforts must now be concentrated
on completing our mission.
现在所有的精力必须聚焦在完成我们的任务上
And if they attack us again?
但如果他们再次袭击我们呢？
The Quark's power must be conserved.
夸克的能量必须保留
Complete the drilling operation!
完成钻孔操作！
Command accepted.
命令已接受
Toba, the primitives will not go unpunished.
Toba, 这些原始人不能不罚
Fleet Leader has just confirmed
舰队首领刚刚证实了
the Dulcians are unsuitable for slave labour.
Dulkis 星人不适合作为奴隶劳工
They will die with their planet.
他们会与他们的星球一起灭亡
Good.
很好
So the sooner we complete the drilling operations,
所以我们越早完成钻孔工作
the sooner they will die.
他们死得越早
Quark, follow!
夸克, 跟上！
(QUARK BLEEPING)
They've gone.
他们走了
That was very rash of you, Jamie.
Those Quarks are appallingly dangerous.
你那样可真是鲁莽, Jamie, 那些夸克可不是一般的危险
Och, they're not so terrible.
噢, 他们并没那么可怕
You know, we dropped a rock on one earlier.
你知道吗, 早先我们用石头砸了一个
Hey, where's Balan? Why wasn't he...
嘿, Balan 在哪儿？为什么他没...
He's dead, Cully. The Dominators killed him.
他死了, Cully, 统领者杀了他
Oh, no! If only we'd managed to get him away, too.
哦, 不！我们要是设法也把他救走就好了
You did your best, Cully.
你尽力了, Cully
It's thanks to you and Jamie
that the rest of us are safe.
得感谢你和 Jamie, 我们其他人才安全了
DOCTOR: I'm afraid not.
Nowhere on the island is safe.
恐怕没有．这个岛上哪里都不安全
Nowhere on the entire planet, come to that!
这整个星球哪里都不安全!
You see, we heard the Dominators say
是这样, 我们听到统领者说
that the Dulcians were unsuitable of slave labour.
Dulkis 星人不适合作为奴隶劳工
- But then they'll leave us in peace!
- Well, no.
- 那他们就会安静地走开！  - 但是, 不是
They said you'll all die with your planet.
他们说你们会同你们的星球一同死亡
Surely they don't mean to destroy Dulkis completely?
他们的意思应该不是要完全毁灭 Dulkis 吧？
- DOCTOR: I'm afraid they do.
- But why? What do they want?
- 恐怕是的  - 但是为什么？他们想要什么？
A large amount of fuel for their invasion fleet.
为他们的侵略舰队提供大量的燃料
But we know that there are no minerals worth having,
但我们知道这里没有他们需要的矿物
at least not on this side of the island.
至少在岛上的这边没有
They're not mining for minerals
or any natural fuel source.
他们不是在采集矿物, 也不需要任何天然的燃料
But their spaceships use atomic power.
We've established that.
但他们的飞船用的是核能, 我们已经推断出来了
But there was no reactor in that ship of theirs,
但他们那艘飞船里面没有反应器
only a radiation storage unit.
只有一个辐射存储单元
You remember how when they landed
你记得不, 他们降落时
it sucked up all the radioactive dust
from the island?
它把这个岛上的放射性尘埃全都吸走了
Yes. So you're saying
that they store radioactive particles
记得, 所以你是说他们把放射性粒子存储起来了
and then convert that energy into power.
然后把它们转换成动力？
Exactly!
正是！
Well, then why are they drilling?
那, 他们为什么要钻孔呢？
Look, I'll show you.
看, 我来跟你展示一下
There are four drill holes
here, here, here and here,
有四个钻孔, 在这里、这里、这里和这里
and one drill hole in the centre.
还有一个钻孔在中间
Now, then, they have rockets mounted
in each of these drill holes,
现在, 他们把火箭装到各个钻孔上
and the centre drill hole is probably
for that atomic seed device.
而中间那个钻孔很可能就是原子播种装置
Oh.
噢
Well, don't you see?
嗯, 明白了吗？
They've chosen this spot because
the crust of the planet is thin.
他们选这个地点是因为这个星球的地壳很薄
They're going to fire the rockets through the crust
他们打算发射火箭穿透地壳
into the magma, the molten core.
进入岩浆, 进而达到地核
ZOE: Then that will almost certainly
fracture the crust of the planet.
那几乎肯定会导致这个星球的地壳裂开
Exactly.
正是
But that will create a volcano.
但那会导致火山啊
And if they explode the atomic
seed device in the middle of that...
而如果他们在那里面引爆那个原子播种装置...
Yes, that's right, Zoe.
是的, 就是这样, Zoe
The whole planet will become one vast
molten mass of radioactive material,
整个星球都会成为一个巨大的放射性材料的熔融体
the fuel store for their fleet.
成为他们u舰队的燃料库
Well, we'll just have to stop them, then.
啊, 我们必须组织他们啊
DOCTOR: Oh, Jamie,
it's not as simple as that, is it?
噢, Jamie, 并没有那么简单的, 是吧？
If only I could get hold of
that atomic seed device,
如果我们能拿到那个原子播种装置
I might be able to defuse it.
我还是有可能拆除它的
Yes, then there'd only be a local
volcanic eruption on the island.
是, 那样的话就只会在这个岛上有个局部的火山爆发了
- Yes... - But how can we get to the device?
- 对...  - 但是我们怎样才能拿到那个装置呢？
Yes, that's the problem.
嗯, 问题就在这里
Doctor, I've just had an idea.
博士, 我有了一个主意
Shush a minute, Jamie, I'm trying to think.
嘘, 等等, Jamie, 我正在思考呢
- Yes, I know you are, but...  - Oh, Jamie!
- 是, 我知道你在思考, 但是... - 噢, Jamie!
Now, listen! Will you listen to me?
现在, 听着！你能听我说吗？
Now, there's a dead-easy way
to get that device thing.
看, 现在有一个非常简单的方法搞到那个设备
- Really?  - Yes, now listen.
- 真的？  - 是的, 听我说
You said they were going to drop it
down the centre hole,
你刚才说他们打算把它扔进中间的钻孔
the one they're drilling outside here.
也就是他们在这里钻的那个
- Right?  - DOCTOR: Yes.
- 对吧？  - 对
Well, it's simple, isn't it?
那, 就简单了, 对不？
All we've got to do is dig a tunnel
through from here to the borehole
我们要做的事情, 就是挖一条隧道, 从这里到那个矿洞
and catch the seed device thing on its way down!
在那个设备下来的时候把它接住！
Oh. Well, it was just an idea.
噢, 但是, 这只是一个想法
But Jamie...
但是, Jamie
It's a brilliant idea!
这是个很神的想法！
It's so simple,
only you could have thought of it.
这个想法如此简单, 只有你才能想到
Oh! Hey?
噢！怎么？
We can get the direction from the periscope.
我们可以从潜望镜里面看好方向
Just line it up with the drilling site.
往钻孔点画一条线
Yes, there's only one snag, though.
Could we complete the tunnel in time?
是的．但还是有一个问题：我们能及时挖通隧道吗？
It'd have to be 12 feet long or more.
至少得有１２英尺
Well, Cully and I could delay
the Dominators' work up there.
这样, Cully 和我可以在上面拖延统领者的工作
ZOE: How?
怎么拖延？
Oh, we're getting very good
at destroying Quarks, aren't we?
噢, 我们很擅长消灭那些夸克, 对吧？
Yes, certainly seems to stop them working.
对, 至少让它们停止工作没有问题
DOCTOR: Yes, that's true,
but you've been lucky so far.
是, 你说得对．但到目前位置你们只是幸运
If only I could devise some sort of weapon for you.
要是我能帮你们设计出某种武器就好了
- Is there anything down here, Cully?
- No, I doubt it.
- 这里有什么东西不, Cully?  - 没, 我怀疑没有
Nothing but survival rations and medical kit.
除了救生口粮和医疗包, 什么也没有
Medical kit? Oh!
医疗包？噢！
It's surprising what you can do
你都想不到我能做些什么
with a few simple chemicals and a little ingenuity.
单凭几种简单的化学品和一点点聪明才智就可以了
Now, come on, we must dig this tunnel.
来, 快点, 我们必须开挖隧道了
- Zoe, give us a direction, will you?  - Right.
- Zoe, 帮我们定一下方向, 好吗？  - 好
On a line from...here.
沿着...这条线
Right! We start the tunnel there.
Get that bunk away, come on.
好！我们从这里开挖, 把那个东西搬走, 快点
That's it, Cully. I'll start with a knife, now...
就这样, Cully．我先用小刀, 看...
This line here.
这条线
I think you'd better let me start it, Jamie.
我觉得你最好让我来开场, Jamie
How are you going to dig through there
with your sonic screwdriver?
你打算用你那个音速起子来挖开这里？
It's a little more than a screwdriver.
Just watch this.
这可不仅仅是一把起子, 看着
(AMAZED CHATTERING, INDISTINCT)
- It's burning straight through!
- Aye, the Doctor's very good.
- 直接就烧穿了  - 啊, 博士很厉害
- Have you finished?  - Yes, just completed.
- 你完成了吗？  - 是的, 刚完成
Good. I shall enjoy destroying
this planet and its creatures.
很好．我要享受一下毁灭这个星球及其生物的过程
Get the seed device.
We will delay no longer.
取那个种子设备, 我们不能再拖延了
Can you see the borehole yet, Jamie?
你能看到矿洞了吗, Jamie?
JAMIE: The ceiling keeps caving in.
顶上开始垮塌了
ZOE: They're coming back!
他们回来了！
Toba's bringing the seed device.
Toba 带着种子设备朝这边来呢
Oh, dear.
噢, 天啦
You will recall all Quarks from their positions
你去把夸克从它们当前位置召回来
and prepare the craft for takeoff.
为飞船起飞做准备
Command accepted.
命令已接受
I will insert the seed device.
我去加入种子设备
Prime the rockets at perimeter boreholes.
将火箭装填到四周的钻孔上
Command accepted.
命令已接受
Very soon we shall see this planet die,
and its creatures with it.
很快我们就能看到这个星球的灭亡了, 连同它的生物一起
Shall I report to Fleet Leader?
要我报告给舰队首领吗？
Inform him the Dominator fleet
may approach on its refuelling orbit.
通知他说统领者舰队可以靠近能量补给轨道了
Command accepted. Quarks, follow.
命令已接受．夸克, 跟上
(QUARKS BLEEPING)
Quickly, Doctor!
快点, 博士！
He's taking the device out of its case now.
他正在把那个装置从箱子里取出来
Oh, Jamie, he'll be too late!
He's putting it in now.
哦, Jamie, 他快来不及了！他要把它放进去了
- It's gone! - DOCTOR: Oh!
- 不见了！  - 噢！
JAMIE: Doctor, have you caught it?
博士, 你接住了吗？
- Oh, Doctor!  - He's coming!
- 噢, 博士！  - 他过来了！
JAMIE: Quick, out.
快, 出去
Well?
怎样？
(LAUGHING)
- Oh, thank goodness!
- We're saved! We're saved, then!
- 噢, 感谢老天！  - 我们得救了, 我们得救了啊！
No, not just yet.
不, 还没有
I've still got to defuse it
before they explode it.
我还得拆除它, 赶在他们引爆它之前
- Oh! Oh, my word!  - ZOE: What?
- 噢！哦, 老天！  - 什么？
Well, it's sealed! It's completely sealed!
啊, 它是封死的！它是完全封死的！
I can't possibly undo it!
我没可能拆除它了！
You mean, all that was for nothing?
We're still going to get blown up?
你是说, 我们的努力都白费了？我们还是会被炸上天？
Yes, I'm afraid so,
unless I can think of some way
是的, 恐怕是, 除非我们想到什么方法...
of getting it off the planet without a...
能够离开这个星球而不...
Have you thought of something?
你是想到什么了吗？
Well, there is a way of getting it off the planet
啊, 的确有一种方法可以离开这个星球
without it doing any harm to any of us at all.
而不对我们所有人造成任何伤害
ZOE: Well, how?
哦, 什么方法？
Ah! But it's not going to be easy...
啊！但可能没有那么容易...
What? What are you going to do?
是什么？你打算怎么做？
Now, just leave it to me, Jamie, hmm?
得, 就交给我吧, Jamie, 嗯？
You, Zoe go back to the Tardis.
你, Zoe, 都回到 TARDIS 去
RAGO: Is all prepared?
都准备好了吗？
Yes, just two more Quarks to arrive.
是的, 就等最后两个夸克到了
Start takeoff procedure.
开始准备起飞
Command accepted.
命令已接受
(CAPSULE BEEPING)
Oh, where is he?
噢, 他在哪儿？
The Dominators' ship, it's away!
统领者的飞船, 开走了！
- Oh!  - Where's the Doctor?
- 噢！  - 博士在哪儿？
Doctor!
博士！
- Hey, where's the bomb thing?
- Oh, did you get rid of it?
- 嘿, 那个炸弹呢？  - 你甩掉它了吗？
- Well, where is it?
- (PANTING) Don't ask so many questions.
- 诶, 它在哪里？  - 别一下问这么多问题
- What?  - There's no time.
- 什么？  - 没有时间了
(EXPLOSIONS)
What's that?
那是什么？
It's the rockets in the other perimeter holes.
是四周那几个钻孔里的火箭
Come along, we'd better get inside the Tardis.
都过来, 我们最好进到 TARDIS 里面去
There's going to be an...
这里会有一场...
(ALL EXCLAIMING)
Toba!
Toba!﻿
Doctor, come on, will you?
The whole place is going to blow up!
博士, 快点, 好吗？这里全部都要爆炸了！
Oh, it's quite all right, Jamie.
The planet is quite safe.
噢, 完全没事的, Jamie．这个星球非常安全
There's just going to be
a localised volcanic eruption.
只会有一场局部的火山爆发
It'll only affect the island.
只会影响这个小岛
Maybe so, but we happen to be on the island.
也许是, 但我们恰巧就在这个岛上
Isn't it beautiful!
是不是很漂亮？
- Oh, my word. What a wonderful sight!
- Fantastic!
- 噢，天啊，多美的景象!  - 壮观！
Listen, will you two stop gaping at that
and get us out of here.
嘿，你俩能不能别感慨了，带我们离开这里
Don't worry, Jamie. We're safe in the Tardis.
别担心, Jamie, 我们在 TARDIS 里面很安全
Are you sure? Has the Tardis
ever been buried in lava before?
你确定吗？ TARDIS 被岩浆掩埋过没有？
- No.
- How can you be so sure we're going to be all right?
- 没有  - 那你怎么能这么肯定我们会没事？
Oh, dear.
噢, 亲爱的
- Is something wrong?
- This has happened before.
- 有什么不对劲吗？  - 这事儿以前也出现过
The fluid links aren't able to take the load. Oh!
流体连接器不工作了．噢！
(ZOE) Mercury vapour!
水银蒸汽！
Oh! This darn thing's stuck! Of all the stupid, idiotic!
噢！这个破玩意儿卡住了！最愚蠢、傻蛋！
- Doctor, The lava's up to the Tardis!
- (ZOE) Doctor
- 博士, 熔岩都快到 TARDIS 了!  - 博士
If only I could unstick this stupid, idiotic...
There we are.
只要我能挪动这个愚蠢、傻蛋的...这下好了
Have you done it? Are we on our way?
你搞定了吗？我们上路了？
It's stopped the fluid links from vaporising.
We shan't suffocate.
流体连接器停止蒸发了。我们不会窒息了
If we don't hurry, we'll be fried by the lava.
如果我们不快点, 就会被熔岩烧成灰了
- Isn't there any way we can get away?
- Well, there IS an emergency unit, but...
- 我们有什么可能逃脱吗？  - 唔, 是有一个紧急设备, 但是...
- I can't possibly use that.
- But this IS an emergency!
- 我不能启用那个  - 但是这就是紧急情况啊
But it moves the Tardis out of the
time-space dimension, out of reality!
但它会把 TARDIS 移出时空维度, 推到现实之外去！
Fine. Reality's getting too hot, anyway!
很好．反正现实已经太热了！
Oh, all right.
噢, 好吧
Here we are.
来看看
Now, then, which end was...?
喏, 哪头是...
Yes...
对了
I can't possibly use this.
We don't know what will happen.
我不能启用这个, 我们不知道可能发生什么!